-==破烂熊乐园倾情奉献==-
-==http://www.ragbear.com==-
福尔摩斯探案集
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
有什么不对头吗?
Something wrong?
一个为了艺术而热爱艺术的人
To the man who loves art for its own sake,
常常是从最不重要
it is frequently in its least important
最为平常的形象中
and lowliest manifestations
得到最大的乐趣
that the keenest pleasure is to be derived.
这么说也没错 福尔摩斯
Oh, if you say so, Holmes.
我高兴的观察到 华生
It is pleasant to me to observe, Watson,
从你诚诚恳恳地为我们的
that you have so far grasped this truth
案件所作的记录中
that in these little records of our cases
你已经掌握了真理
which you have been good enough to draw up,
而且我肯定地讲 你有时还加以润色
and I am bound to say, occasionally embellish,
你加以突出的并不是那些我曾经
that you have given prominence not so much
参与过的著名案件的侦破
to the many cause celebes and sensational trials
和轰动一时的审讯
in which I have figured,
而是那些本身情景
but rather to those incidents
可能是平凡琐碎的案件
which have given room for those faculties
但给人发挥逻辑推论才能的余地
of deduction and logical synthesis
这正是我的特殊研究领域
which I have made my special province.
很高兴你这么说 福尔摩斯
Kind of you to say so, Holmes.
也许你确有错误
You have erred, perhaps...
错就错在...
you have erred...
总想把每项记录
in attempting to put color and life
都写的生动一些
into each of your statements,
而不是将你的任务限制
instead of confining yourself to placing upon record
在记述事件因果关系的推理上
that severe reasoning from cause to effect
这实际上是事物唯一值得注意的特点
which is really the only notable feature about the thing.
你用这个烟斗时
You are always in a disputatious mood
总是在争论
when you choose that pipe.
在这个问题上 我看我对你
It seems to me that I have done you
还是十分公正的
full justice in the matter.
不 不 不...
No, no, no, no, no, no,
这不是我自私或是自大
it is not selfishness or even conceit.
如果我要求公正地对待我的艺术
If I claim full justice for my art,
是因为犯罪是常有的事
it is because crime is common;
逻辑却是难得的东西
logic is rare.
因此 应该详细记述的
Therefore, it is upon logic rather than upon crime
是逻辑而不是罪行
that you should dwell.
你把本该是讲授的课程
You have degraded what should have been a course
降级成了一连串的故事
of lectures into a series of tales.
没错 福尔摩斯
Really, Holmes,
我想我的拙文达不到你的要求
I hardly think my poor scribbling deserve that.
可我的故事终究让你家喻户晓
They have, after all, made your name a household word.
啐 我亲爱的老伙计
Oh, pshaw, my dear fellow,
对于公众 不善观察的公众
what do the public, the great unobservant public,
他们不可能从一个人的牙齿认出他是编织工
who can hardly tell a weaver by his tooth
或从一个人的左拇指看出他是排字工
or a compositor by his left thumb,
他们会关心分析和推理的细微区别吗
care about the finer shades of analysis and deduction?
但是 如果你确实写的太繁琐
But, indeed, if you are trivial,
我也不能责备你 作大案子的时代已经过去了
I cannot blame you, the days of the great cases are past.
一个人 或至少是一个罪犯
Man, or at least criminal man,
已经没有了过去的冒险和创新精神
has lost all enterprise and originality.
肯定没有
Oh, surely not.
恐怕是的
I fear so.
我的小行业
As to my little practice,
似乎也退化到了处理家庭琐事
it seems to be degenerating into an agency
寻找丢失的铅笔
for recovering ost lead pencils
替寄宿学校的姑娘们出出主意
and giving advice to young ladies from boarding schools.
亲爱的朋友
My dear, dear friend,
你怎么能这么说呢
how can you say such a thing?
我想 我已经身处事业谷底了
I think I have touched bottom, finally.
不管怎么说 这张我今早收到的条子
However, this note I had this morning
我想标志了我的最低点
marks my zero-point, I fancy.
老天啊 谁寄来的
Well, goodness, who is it from?
读一读
Read it.
亲爱的福尔摩斯先生
Dear Mr. Holmes:
我急切的想找您商量
I am very anxious to consult you
关于我是否应该接受别人聘请我
as to whether I should or should not accept a situation
当家庭女教师的问题
which has been offered to me as a governess.
我明天十点半来拜访你
I shall call at half-past ten tomorrow
如果不麻烦你的话
if I do not inconvenience you.
你的忠实的维奥莱特・亨特
Yours faithfully, Violet Hunter.
我不得不承认对这信的内容
I must confess to being somewhat puzzled
有点疑惑 亨特小姐
by the contents of your letter, Miss, uh, Hunter,
因为你咨询的问题
since the matter on which you seek advice
不在我的工作范畴之内
is somewhat outside my sual field of expertise.
是的 我知道
Yes, I am aware of that.
但是你会原谅我麻烦你的
But you will excuse my troubling you, I am sure,
我确定 因为我最近的经历很不寻常
since I have recently had a very strange experience.
是吗
Indeed?
我没有父母或任何亲戚
As I have no parents or relations of any sort
可以请教
from whom I could ask advice,
我想也许你会好心
I thought perhaps you would be kind enough
告诉我应该怎么办
to tell me what I should do.
我将会高兴地尽力为您服务
I shall be happy to serve you in any way I can;
请 继续
pray, proceed.
西郊有一家出名的家教介绍所
There is a well-known agency for governesses in the West End
叫维斯塔维 我最近每周都要到那里
called Westaway's, and I have lately been calling there
询问是否有
about once a week in order to see whether
适合我的工作
anything has turned up which might suit me.
经理是斯托珀小姐
It is managed by Miss Stoper.
她坐在自己的办公室里
She sits alone in her own office,
求职的女性
and the ladies who are seeking employment
在接待室等待接见
wait in the anteroom,
之后挨个进去
and are then shown in one by one,
她会在记录本上查看
when she consults her ledgers and sees whether
有没有适合求职者的工作
she has anything which might suit them.
格林小姐在我们的登记簿上已经很长时间了
Miss Green has been on our books for some years
有很好的资历
and has excellent references.
实际上 她的前任雇主
In fact, were it not for the swift return to Kuala Lampur
对她非常满意
of her present employer,
如果不是急于举家返回库阿拉兰珀
who finds her most satisfactory,
她今天也不会在这里待选
she would not be available today for your consideration.
谢谢 格林小姐
Thank you, Miss Green.
她就可以
Oh, that will do.
我不能要求比这更好的了
I could not ask for anything better.
好极了 非常好
Oh, capital, capital.
太好了
Splendid.
请坐 亨特小姐
Please be seated, Miss Hunter.
你是来寻找职位的吧 小姐
Now, then, you are looking for a situation, miss?
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
做家庭女教师?
As a governess?
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
你要求多少薪水?
And what salary do you ask?
我以前在斯彭斯芒罗上校那里
I had four pounds a month in my last place
是每月4英镑
with Colonel Spence Munro.
他给她的待遇已经很高了 鲁卡斯尔先生
He has given her an excellent reference, Mr. Rucastle.
毫无疑问 毫无疑问
Oh, doubtless, doubtless,
可是每月4英镑?
but four pounds a month?
如果那太多了...
If that seems too much...
太多了?不 不
Too much? oh, tut, tut,
怎么会有人出这么可怜的小数目
how could anyone offer so pitiful a sum to a lady
给一位如此有吸引力和造诣的女士?
with such attraction and accomplishments?
我的造诣 先生
My accomplishments, sir,
可能不如你所想像的那样深
may be less than you imagine.
懂一点法文 一点德文 音乐 绘画...
A little French, a little German, music, drawing...
啧 啧
Oh, tut, tut,
这些都不是主要问题
that is quite beside the question.
关键是你有没有
The point is, have you or have you not
具备一位有教养女士的举止和风度?
the bearing and deportment of a lady?
简单地说就是这一句话
I mean, that is it in a nutshell.
我希望自己有 先生
I would hope to have lady like qualities, sir.
如果你没有
If you have not,
你就不适合教育一个
then you are not fitted for the rearing of a child
家世和才华
whose background and qualities point
直指成功未来的孩子
to a brilliant future.
倘若你有 为什么竟有人会要求你
And if you have, why, how can any gentleman ask you
屈尊接受少于三位数的薪水?
to condescend to accept anything under three figures?
三位数 先生
Three figures, sir?
这是我提供的薪水 女士
Your salary with me, madam,
一年一百英镑
would commence at a hundred pounds a year.
我都不知道说什么了
I hardly know what to say.
这也是我的习惯
It has also been my custom to advance my young ladies
预付一部分的薪水给我的年轻的小姐
a small portion of their salary beforehand,
好让她们应付旅费上的开支
so that they might meet any little expenses
并置办一些衣服
of their journey and their wardrobe.
谢谢 先生
Thank you, sir.
可否问问你住在什么地方吗
May I ask where you live?
汉普郡 可爱的乡村地区
Oh, Hampshire, charming rural place,
铜山毛榉
The Copper Beeches,
离温切斯特只有5英里
five miles on the further side of Winchester.
是最可爱的乡村
Oh, it is the most lovely country,
亲爱的小姐 还有最可爱的老房子
my dear young lady, and the dearest old country house.
我的职责呢?
And my duties, sir?
我很想了解一下
I should be glad to know what they would be.
一个孩子 刚刚六岁的小淘气
One child, one dear little romper just six years old.
多好啊
How charming.
斯托珀小姐 你要是能看到
Oh, Miss Stoper, if you could only see him
他用拖鞋打死蟑螂
killing cockroaches with a slipper,
一眨眼的功夫 三只就报销了
three of them gone before you could wink.
很聪明
Very clever.
我唯一的工作
My sole duties, then,
就是 照顾一个孩子?
are to take charge of a single child?
不 不 不...
Oh, no, no, no, no, no, no,
不是唯一的 我亲爱的年轻的小姐
not sole, my dear young lady.
还有什么?
Oh, what else, then?
你的责任是
Well, your duty would be,
我肯定你聪明的头脑能意识到
as I am sure your good sense would suggest,
听候我妻子的任何命令
to obey any little commands that my wife might give.
你是说命令?
You said commands?
假如有的话 当然
Provided, of course,
这些命令是一位小姐
that they were such commands as any young lady
理应遵从的话
might with propriety obey.
你看 没有任何困难吧?
You see no difficulty?
不 什么都行
None, whatsoever.
很乐意能够帮得上忙
I should be happy to make myself useful.
太好了
Quite so.
说说服装  比如说 我们都是我们喜欢时尚
In dress, for example, we are faddy people,
你知道 时尚癖 但心眼不坏
you know, Miss Hunter, faddy, but kind-hearted.
倘若我们给你衣服
And if you were asked to wear any dress
让你穿的话
that we might give you,
你不会反对我们小小的怪癖吧?
you would not object to our little whims, huh?
为什么 不会啊
Why, um, no.
叫你坐在这里 坐在那里
Or to sit here, or to sit there,
不会让你不高兴吧
and that would not be offensive to you?
不会
No.
或者你来之前 把头发剪短一点
Or to cut your hair quite short before you come to us?
剪短头发?
Cut my hair?
剪得很短
Quite short.
我想这可能不行
Well, I am afraid that's quite impossible.
恐怕这点很重要
And I am afraid it is quite essential.
这是我妻子的小小癖好
It's a little fancy of my wife's,
夫人们的癖好 我亲爱的小姐
and ladies' fancies, my dear madam,
夫人们的爱好必须得考虑
ladies' fancies must be consulted.
那么 你不打算剪掉头发?
So you won't cut your hair?
不 先生 实在不行
No, sir, I'm afraid I could not.
好吧 真可惜
Ah, well, it is a pity,
因为其它方面你实在很合适
because in other respects you might have done very nicely.
既然这样 斯托普小姐
In that case, Miss Stoper,
我最好再看几个姑娘
I had best inspect some more of your ladies.
亨特小姐
Miss Hunter,
你愿意将姓名保留在登记簿上吗?
do you desire your name to be kept upon our books?
如果你乐意的话 斯托普小姐
If you please, Miss Stoper.
其实 登记似乎也没有什么用处
Well, really, it seems rather useless,
既然你用这种方式拒绝了最优厚的待遇
since you refused the most excellent offer in this fashion,
我们很难再为你寻找
you could hardly expect us to exert ourselves
一个这样的机会
to find another such opening for you.
抱歉 斯托普小姐 但是我的头发...
I'm sorry, Miss Stoper, but my hair...
再会 亨特小姐
Good day, Miss Hunter.
到底为什么他会让你剪短头发?
Now, why on earth should he want you to cut your hair?
不知道
I don't know.
奇怪的要求
A very strange fact.
正如你所见 福尔摩斯先生
As you may observe, Mr. Holmes,
我的头发很浓密
my hair is somewhat luxuriant
有着栗子般特殊的色泽
and a rather peculiar tint of chestnut.
颇为艺术 在我看来
And most artistic, if I may so observe.
考虑到这些
It has been considered so.
我不能这么轻易的
I simply couldn't think of sacrificing it
为了满足别人就把它牺牲掉
in such an offhand manner.
恐怕确实是不可能的
Well, I should think not, indeed.
当时我就是这种感觉
Oh, such was my feeling at the time.
第二天我开始想
The next day I was inclined to think
自己是不是错了
that I had made a mistake,
第三天 我肯定自己错了
and the day after I was sure of it,
我收到了这位先生的信
when I received a letter from the gentleman himself.
我把它带来了 这就念给你听
I have it here, and I will read it to you.
亲爱的亨特小姐:
Dear Miss Hunter:
斯托普小姐将你的地址告诉了我
Miss Stoper has kindly given me your address,
所以写信想问一下
and I write from here to ask
你有没有重新考虑自己的决定
whether you have reconsidered your decision.
我们愿意支付每季度30英镑
We are willing to give 30 pounds a quarter,
也就是每年120英镑来补偿你
or 120 pounds a year, so as to recompense you
因为我们癖好可能带来的小小不便
for any little inconvenience which our fads may cause you.
那你的头发呢?
And your hair?
他很坚决
He is insistent.
"考虑到你的头发 无疑非常遗憾
As regards your hair, it is no doubt a pity,
尤其是在我们短暂的会面中我就不禁赞美
especially as I could not help remarking its beauty
你美丽的头发
during our short interview.
但恐怕我必须坚持这一点
But I am afraid I must remain firm upon this point,
惟愿增加的一点薪水
and I only hope that the increased salary
也许足以补偿你的损失"
may recompense you for the loss.
可以吗?
Will it?
我已经决定接受了
My mind is made up that I will accept the offer.
然而我想 在走这最后一步前
I thought, however, that before taking the final step,
最好把事情的全部经过
I should like to submit the whole matter
都告诉你
for your consideration.
亲爱的亨特小姐
My dear Miss Hunter,
既然你已经决定了
as your mind is already made up,
事情就已经解决了
the matter is settled.
但是 如果你发现
But, if at any time you should find yourself
有任何的疑惑或者遇到危险
in any doubt or danger
危险?
Danger?
你预见到什么危险?
What danger do you foresee?
如果能够确定 那就不叫危险了
There seems to be a danger, if we could define it.
但不论什么时候 白天或晚上
But at any time, day or night,
打一个电报我就来帮你
a telegram will bring me down to your help.
这足够了
Then that is enough.
我会马上写信回复鲁卡斯尔先生的
I shall write to Mr. Rucastle at once,
现在可以安心的去汉普郡了
and go down to Hampshire quite easy in my mind now.
谢谢
Thank you.
福尔摩斯?
Well, Holmes?
我可不会让我的姐妹接受这样的工作
I should allow no sister of mine to accept such a situation.
杰夫罗・鲁卡斯尔 汉普郡温切斯特附近 铜山毛榉
这是我的仆人 托勒 他喜欢安全一点
That's my man, Toller, he likes to keep it secure.
但你能理解吧 亨特小姐
But you look apprehensive, Miss Hunter.
完全可以 鲁卡斯尔先生
Not at all, Mr. Rucastle.
太好了 太好了
Good, good.
你肯定是爱德华
You must be Edward,
我很期待见到你
I have looked forward to meeting you.
爱德华少爷
Master Edward,
这是你新的家庭教师 亨特小姐
this is your new governess, Miss Hunter.
看来你给亨特小姐准备了见面礼
Oh, I see you have a present for Miss Hunter.
干得好 好枪法
Oh, well done, good shot.
铜山毛榉?鲁卡斯尔先生
Copper Beeches, Mr. Rucastle?
全死了 亨特小姐 大部分都死了
All dead, Miss Hunter, mostly dead.
就是这里 进来 进来
Here we are, then, come in, come in.
托勒夫人 这位是维奥莱特・亨特
Oh, Mrs. Toller, this is Miss Violet Hunter,
她是爱德华小主人的家教
who is taking up the position of governess to Master Edward.
你好 亨特小姐
How do you do, Miss Hunter?
你的房间已经准备好了
Your room is all ready for you.
谢谢
Thank you.
现在去 托勒 把行李搬过来
Come along now, Toller, fetch the trunk.
亨特小姐 等你休息过后
Oh, Miss Hunter, after you are refreshed from your journey,
我带你去游览铜山毛榉
I'll take you on a tour of The Copper Beeches.
房子很大 鲁卡斯尔先生
The premises is certainly extensive, Mr. Rucastle.
是的 这么大的房子需要好好防护
Oh, yes, and the extensive premises need protection.
看 是不是很漂亮
Look in here, isn't he a beauty?
别害怕 亨特小姐
Don't be frightened, Miss Hunter,
它是卡罗 我的看门犬
it's only Carlo, my mastiff.
我称它为我的 但实际上
I call him mine, but in fact,
托勒是唯一能驯服它的人
Toller is the only man that can do anything with him.
他晚上就放它出来
He lets him loose at night,
上帝保佑那些置身它利牙之下的路人
and God help any trespasser he lays his fangs upon.
我们每天喂他一次 但喂的不多
We feed him once a day, and not too much then,
所以他总是很饥饿
so that he is always keen as mustard.
看在上帝的份上 亨特小姐
Oh, for goodness sakes, Miss Hunter,
晚上无故跨过这道门槛的话
under no pretext set foot across this threshold at night;
很可能会丧命的
it's as much as your life is worth.
鲁卡斯尔夫人马上就来
Mrs. Rucastle will be here shortly,
她会让你知道她有多么高兴
and she will tell you herself how delighted she is
你接受了这个工作
you are able to accept this situation.
你的待遇非常丰厚 先生
Your offer was a most generous one, sir.
可是 我还是对你们的要求很好奇
Though, well, I am still curious about the conditions.
你是说我小小的癖好?
My little fads and fancies, you mean?
是的
Yes.
其实没什么
But they're nothing at all.
我妻子特别喜欢一种颜色
My wife is very fond of a particular shade
铁蓝色
of electric blue,
她希望你早上能够在家
and she would like you to wear such a dress indoors
穿这样的衣服
in the morning.
但是我并没有这样的衣服
But I do not have such a dress.
但我们有
Ah, but we have one.
说到坐在这里 那里
As to sitting here or there
或者用任何方法逗你笑
or amusing yourself in any matter indicated,
不会让你感到不方便吧?
well, that need cause you no inconvenience, need it?
不
No.
你好 亨特小姐
How do you do, Miss Hunter?
很抱歉没去迎接你
I'm sorry I was not here to greet you,
微有小恙在身
a slight indisposition.
我想你现在已经好多了吧?
I trust you are feeling better now?
好很多了 谢谢
Much better, thank you.
我刚才在和亨特女士讲蓝衣服的事
I was just telling Miss Hunter about the blue dress.
是的 我想那衣服你穿肯定很合身
Yes, I think it would fit you very well.
我在想这案子究竟会是
I wonder what desperate circumstances
在什么样的恐怖环境下引起的?
could occasion such an appeal?
我曾想过七种假设
I have devised seven separate explanations,
每种都适用于现在我们知道的事实
each of which would cover the facts as far as we know them.
你更倾向于哪种 福尔摩斯?
Oh, and which one do you favor, Holmes?
目前为止还没有比较偏好的
At the moment, I have no favorites.
材料 材料 材料 没有粘土我没法做出砖头来
Data, data, data, I cannot make bricks without clay.
能远离贝克街的
Well, it's nice to get away from the fogs
乌烟瘴气太好了
of Baker Street now and again.
多么漂亮的小农房啊
What delightful little farms these are,
你不觉得他们清新美丽吗?
don't you agree, aren't they fresh and beautiful?
你知道 华生
You know, Watson,
我性格被诅咒了的一个表现就是
it is one of the curses of having a mind
每件事都要和自己研究的
with a turn like mine that I must look at everything
特殊问题联系起来
with reference to my own special subject.
但这不会让风景的美丽
Well, it doesn't make the scenery
有损一分一毫 不是吗?
any less admirable, does it?
你看这些零星散布的农房
You look at these scattered houses,
他们的秀丽给你留下深刻印象
and you are impressed by their beauty.
我看到它们时 心里涌现的想法是
I look at them, and the only thought which comes to me
总感觉它们非常孤立
is a feeling of their isolation
会使可能发生的罪行得不到应有惩罚
and of the impunity with which crime may be committed there.
我的天啊
Good heavens,
谁会把犯罪和这些可爱的老农房联系起来
who would associate crime with these dear old homesteads?
它们总使我充满恐怖之感
They always filled me with a certain horror.
这是我的信条 根据我的经验
It is my belief, Watson, founded upon my experience,
伦敦最卑贱 最恶劣的小巷
that the lowest and vilest alleys in London
也不会发生比这令人愉悦的美丽的乡村里
do not present a more dreadful record of sin
更恐怖的犯罪行为了
than does the smiling and beautiful countryside.
向我们求援的这位小姐
Had this young lady who appeals to us for help
要是住在温切斯特
gone to live in Winchester,
我绝不会为她担心
I should never have had a fear for her.
但危险在于这五英里之外的农村
It is the five miles of country which makes the danger.
这能说明什么 福尔摩斯?
What can it mean, Mr. Holmes?
恐怕没有足够资料 我们还不能下定论
We cannot theorize without data, I'm afraid.
请继续说 亨特小姐
Please, continue, Miss Hunter.
首先
In the first place,
总的来说
I may say that I have met, on the whole,
我没有受到
with no actual ill-treatment from
鲁卡斯尔夫妇的虐待
Mr. and Mrs. Rucastle.
但我很不放心
But I am not easy in my mind about them,
而且也不能理解
and I cannot understand them.
不能理解什么
What can't you understand?
为他们行为的辩解的理由
The reasons for their conduct.
我到铜山毛榉后 头两天
For two days after my arrival at the Copper Beeches,
生活很平静
my life was very quiet.
第三天 我吃过早饭下楼到绘画室
On the third, I went downstairs after breakfast to find
去找鲁卡斯尔夫妇
Mr. and Mrs. Rucastle in the drawing room.
鲁卡斯尔先生提到了那件衣服
Mr. Rucastle informed me that a dress,
把一件铁蓝色的衣服
an electric blue dress,
放在了我的卧室里
had been laid out for me in my bedroom,
要求我穿上
and asked me to put it on.
我照他说的做了
I did as he requested.
太棒了 亨特小姐 太棒了
Oh, superb, Miss Hunter, oh, quite superb.
你不觉得吗
Do you not agree?
再合身不过了
It could not be a better fit,
就像特地量身制作的一样
not if you had been measured for it.
请坐下 亨特小姐
Please, be so good as to sit down, Miss Hunter.
完美 太好了 真完美
Oh, perfect, I mean, it's quite, quite perfect.
坐这里 如果不介意的话 亨特小姐
Over here, if you don't mind, Miss Hunter.
看啊 看啊 多么漂亮
There, there, there now, excellent.
你觉得舒适吗?
Are you quite comfortable?
是的 谢谢
Yes, thank you.
你希望我在这里坐多久 先生?
How long do you wish me to remain here, sir?
一个小时 可能更久
Oh, an hour, perhaps, perhaps longer.
一个小时?
An hour?
但是 我保证绝对不会是无聊的一个小时
Oh, but not, I assure you, an hour of tedium.
让我们试试逗你开心
Let us see how we can best entertain and divert you.
喜欢好玩的故事吗 亨特小姐?
Do you enjoy funny stories, Miss Hunter?
是啊 为什么?
Why, yes.
好吧 那我就给你说几个
Well, then, I shall tell you some,
但我保证这都是真事儿
and all of them, I assure you, absolutely true.
让我给你讲讲乔治的事
Let me tell you about George.
他这个人极其特别
He is the most extraordinary character.
是这样
Well, it seems,
有人想去温切斯特
somebody wanted to find his way to Winchester,
然后乔治 真是个怪人
and George, he really is such an eccentric,
你可能会把他错当成稻草人
you might mistake him for a scarecrow,
我是说 他的腿总是劈开
I mean, his legs are all astray,
他的胳膊总是这样
his arms always thrust out like this,
他的头活像一个大头菜
his head shaved like a turnip,
他头上还带着与众不同的帽子
and on his head he wore the most extraordinary hat
然后 鲁卡斯尔先生
Then Mr. Rucastle,
在房间的另一边上蹿下跳
walking up and down on the other side of the room,
开始讲述我听过的
began to tell me a series of the funniest stories
最好笑的故事
I've ever listened to.
你们想不出他有多滑稽
You cannot imagine how comical he was.
我都笑累了
I laughed till I was quite weary.
两天以后完全相同的情景
Two days later this same performance
又上演了一遍
was gone through again.
这是上帝的和平 没人能够理解
This is the peace of God, that passes all understanding.
我的天哪!已经一个小时了?
Oh, bless my soul, is that the hour already?
时间过的真快 太有趣了 先生
Time has passed very quickly, and most amusingly, sir.
很高兴你这么说
Well, I'm glad to hear you say so.
现在干该去自己的工作了
But now, it is time for you to attend to your duties,
去换掉衣服
so go and change your dress,
然后去照顾小爱德华
and then look to little Edward in the nursery.
你不难想象 福尔摩斯先生
You can easily imagine, Mr. Holmes,
我是多么难以理解这种
how curious I became as to what the meaning
异乎寻常的表演
of this extraordinary performance could be.
我察觉到他们总是小心的让我脸背对窗户
Since my face was always turned away from the window,
我开始好奇想看看
I became consumed with the desire to see
背后到底有什么东西
what was going on behind my back.
下一次的表演中
On the very next occasion,
我想办法在手里握了一块镜子
I managed to conceal a small piece of mirror in my hand.
噢 乔治 我不能告诉你...
Oh, George, I can't tell you -
当我笑的时候
In the midst of my laughter,
我将手帕举到了眼前
I raised my handkerchief to my eyes,
稍微摆弄了一下
and was able with a little management
看看我背后有什么
to see all there was behind me.
什么也没有
There was nothing,
至少我第一印象如此
at least that was my first impression.
第二次看的时候
At second glance, however,
我察觉到有一个长胡子的男人
I perceived that there was a bearded man
靠在场地的围栏上
leaning against the railings which bordered our field,
认真的朝这边张望
and was looking up earnestly at the house.
我把举着的手帕放低 瞥了鲁卡斯尔夫人一眼
I lowered my handkerchief and glanced at Mrs. Rucastle,
发现她正犀利的盯着我
to find her eyes fixed upon me in a most searching gaze.
她没说什么
She said nothing,
但我相信她已经猜出我手中有镜子
but I'm convinced she divined I had a mirror in my hand.
杰夫罗 那边有个不三不四的家伙
Jephro, there is an impertinent fellow
盯着亨特小姐呢
who stares up at Miss Hunter.
真的?
Oh, does he indeed?
不是你的朋友吧? 亨特小姐
No friend of yours, Miss Hunter?
不是 我在这里一个人也不认识
No, I know no one in these parts.
天啊 真是不礼貌
Oh, dear me, how very impertinent.
不可容忍
Quite intolerable.
请你转过身去
Kindly turn around, Miss Hunter,
示意他离开
and motion him to go away.
当然还是不理他更好
Surely it would be better if we took no notice.
什么 让他一直这样看下去吗?
What, and have him loitering here always?
不 转过去 亨特小姐
No, turn around, Miss Hunter,
像这样挥手让他离开
and wave him away like this.
这是一周之前的事
That was a week ago,
之后我就不再坐到窗户边
and from that time I have not sat in the window,
也没穿过蓝衣服
nor have I worn the blue dress,
更没见过那个长胡子的男人
nor seen the man with the beard.
但是 发生了别的事情
But something else occurred,
让你最终急匆匆来找我的事情
an event which caused you to summon me with such urgency?
是 是的 福尔摩斯先生
Yes, yes, oh, Mr. Holmes,
我从没有这么害怕过
I've never been so frightened.
不要害怕 亨特小姐
Do not distress yourself, Miss Hunter,
打起精神来 告诉我们是什么
compose yourself, and then tell us what it was.
房子边上有个塔楼
There is a turret to the house
看起来根本没人住在里面
which appears not to be inhabited at all.
一扇朝向那边通往托勒家的门
A door which faces that which leads into the quarters
可以从那扇门进入那间塔楼
of the Tollers opens into the turret,
但它通常是锁着的
but it is invariably locked.
直到昨天我才有机会
It was only yesterday that the chance came
走过那扇门
for me to pass beyond the door.
托勒?
Toller?
是的
Yes.
原来确实是你
So it was you, then.
我看到门开着的时候就想到了
I thought it must be when I saw the door open.
我很害怕
I'm so frightened.
我亲爱的女士
Oh, my dear young lady,
是什么吓着了你
oh, my dear young lady, what has frightened you,
我亲爱的年轻小姐
my dear young lady?
我太愚蠢了
I - I was foolish enough
跑到了锁着的塔楼上
to go up into the shuttered turret.
你注意到是锁着的?
You noticed it was shuttered then?
是的
Yes.
照相也是我的爱好之一
Photography is one of my hobbies.
我把那间房子作为黑室
I have made my dark room up there.
多么循规蹈矩的年轻小姐啊
What an observant young lady one has come upon.
里面的光线很昏暗 非常阴森恐怖
It was so lonely and eerie in this dim light
我很害怕 于是跑了出来
that I was frightened and ran out again.
心里还是很害怕
It's so dreadfully still in there.
只是这些?
Only that?
怎么了?你认为还有什么原因?
Why, yes, what do you think, what other reason?
你觉得我为什么要锁上门?
Why do you think I keep that door locked?
我确实不知道
I'm sure I don't know.
为了不让无关的人进去
It is to keep people out who have no business there,
你明白吗?
do you see?
要是我早知道...
I'm sure if I had known
你现在知道了
Well, you know now.
如果你再敢踏上那台阶
And if you ever set foot across that threshold again,
我就把你扔给看门犬
I'll throw you to the mastiff.
我太害怕了不知道该怎么办
I was so terrified that I didn't know what to do.
然后我想到了你 福尔摩斯先生
Then I thought of you, Mr. Holmes.
我今早从那里轻易脱身
I had no difficulty in getting leave to come
来到温切斯特
to Winchester this morning,
但我必须在3点之前回去
but I must be back by 3:00 o'clock,
因为鲁卡斯尔夫妇要去别人家拜访
for Mr. and Mrs. Rucastle are going on a visit
所以整夜都不回来
and will be away all evening,
我得照顾孩子
so that I must look after the child.
我把我的奇遇都告诉给你了 福尔摩斯先生
Now I've told you all of my adventures, Mr. Holmes.
到底是怎么回事 我该怎么办?
What does it mean, and what should I do?
那个少有言语的孩子爱德华有朋友吗?
Does the unspeakable child Edward have a friend?
有
Yes, uh,
农场里一个同样可怕的孩子
an equally unpleasant child at one of the farm cottages.
太好了
Splendid.
华生医生和我会在4点半
Dr. Watson and I will arrive at the Copper Beeches
准时到达铜山毛榉
at 4:30 precisely.
但在我们到达之前 有一两件事
But before then, there are one or two things
我希望你去做
I should like you to do.
如果我不是认为你一位卓越的女性
I would not ask this of you, Miss Hunter,
我是不会让你做这些的
if I did not think you were quite an exceptional woman.
托勒太太
Mrs. Toller?
托勒太太 爱德华可能把自己锁在了地下室了
Mrs. Toller, I think Edward has locked himself in the cellar
地下室?
The cellar?
我哪里都找不到他
Well, I can't find him anywhere,
已经过了喝茶的时间
and it is past his tea time.
我也发现了 我不明白为什么
Well, just the same, I don't see why Master Edward
爱德华少爷要把自己关在地下室里
would have locked himself in the cellar.
早些时候门是开着的
Well, the door was open earlier,
我看见托勒拿着一个瓶子出来
I saw Toller come out with a bottle.
可能他去找蟑螂了吧
Perhaps he went down to look for cockroaches.
门锁着
It's locked.
打开了 小姐
There you are, miss.
您先请
After you.
我们的目的地
Our destination.
福尔摩斯 你确定看门犬没有被放出来吗?
Holmes, can we be quite sure the mastiff isn't loose?
到达房子之前什么也不能确定
We can be sure of nothing until we reach the house.
天啊 那是什么
Good God, what was that?
快来
Come quickly.
往左走 福尔摩斯先生
To the left, Mr. Holmes.
这里肯定有发生过恐怖的事情
There has been some villainy here.
看起来有人从房顶上爬过来过
It looks as though someone has gone across the roof.
爱丽丝 爱丽丝...
Alice, Alice, Alice, Alice, Alice.
爱丽丝?
Alice?
我女儿呢?
Where is my daughter?
我还要问你呢
That is for me to ask you that.
他女儿?
His daughter?
贼 你们这些间谍 贼间谍
Thieves, you spies, thieves and spies.
我抓到你了 不是吗
I have caught you, have I?
你在我手心里了
I have you in my power.
我来好好伺候你
I'll serve you.
他什么意思?
What does he mean?
他去放狗了
He's gone for the dog.
华生
Watson.
有人放了狗
Someone has loosed the dog.
它已经两天没有喂食了
It's not been fed for two days.
快点 不然就迟了
Quick, before it's too late.
还昏迷着
Still unconscious.
我已经尽力了
I've done what I can for him,
他需要立刻进行手术
he now needs a surgeon as soon as possible.
我已经派托勒叫鲁卡瑟尔夫人
I've dispatched Toller to Mrs. Rucastle
去找医生
to summon such assistance.
小姐 可惜你不曾让我知道
Oh, miss, it's a pity you didn't let me know
你的打算
what you were planning,
我本来早点可以告诉你 省得你费那么大的劲
I could have told you your pains were wasted.
很明显 托勒太太
It's clear Mrs. Toller knows
比谁都了解这件事
more of this matter than anyone else.
是的 先生 我知道 我...
Well, yes, sir, I do, and I'm...
我已经准备好把我知道的一切告诉你
I'm ready enough to tell you what I know.
但是如果警察要介入这件事
But if there's police court business over this,
记住我是爱丽丝小姐的朋友
you will remember I was Miss Alice's friend.
爱丽丝小姐?
Miss Alice?
鲁卡斯尔先生第一次结婚时的女儿
Mr. Rucastle's daughter by his first marriage.
也就是锁着的塔楼的秘密
Ah, the mystery of the shuttered turret.
托勒太太 请坐下说
Mrs. Toller, please sit down.
告诉我你知道的一切
Now, tell me all you know.
她在家里从来没有开心过
Well, she was never happy at home,
爱丽丝小姐
Miss Alice wasn't,
从他父亲再次结婚开始
from the time that her father married again.
她...她开始有点冷漠
She - she was slighted like,
什么话也不说
and had no say in anything.
可是... 事情开始好转
But - but it didn't became bad for her
当她遇到了富勒先生
until after she met Mr. Fowler.
请问 谁是富勒先生?
And pray, who is Mr. Fowler?
他是爱丽丝小姐年轻的男朋友
Well, he was Miss Alice's young man.
你... 你可能看到过他在附近
You - you might have seen him hanging about,
场地边的路上转悠
out in the road by the field.
是的
Yes.
富勒先生的卷入
And how did Mr. Fowler's involvement
又给绝望的爱丽丝带来了什么?
bring Miss Alice to her distressing circumstances?
据我所知
Well, as far as I could learn,
爱丽丝小姐有母亲遗嘱里
Miss Alice had rights of her own
赋予的权利
under her late mother's will,
但她是如此安静和忍让
but she was so quiet and patient, she was,
从来不提权利的事
she never said a word about them
而是将一切都交给鲁卡斯尔先生处理
but just left everything in Mr. Rucastle's hands.
他知道和她在一起可以很放心
Well, he knew he was safe with her,
但一旦有丈夫掺和进来
but when there was a chance of a husband coming forward,
他一定会要求在法律范围内应得的东西
who would ask for all the law will give him,
于是她父亲认为是该制止这事的时候了
well, then, her father thought it time to put a stop on it.
他要女儿签署一个字据
He wanted her to sign a paper
声明不管她结婚与否
so that whether she married or not,
他都可以用她的钱
he could use her money.
由于她不愿意签
Well, when she wouldn't do it,
他就一直闹
he kept worrying her, worrying her,
直到女儿得了脑炎
till she got brain-fever;
徘徊在死亡的边缘六个星期之久
for six weeks she was at death's door.
最后她逐渐康复
When she got better at last,
但已经骨瘦如柴
all worn to a shadow,
美丽的头发也剪掉了
and with her beautiful hair cut off,
他把她安排到塔楼去住
he moved her to the turret room,
把她囚禁在那里
where she was kept prisoner.
但这不能让她的男朋友变心
But that didn't make no change in her young man,
他仍然对她十二分的忠诚
and he stuck to her true as a man could be.
然后鲁卡斯尔先生把亨特小姐从伦敦带过来
And then Mr. Rucastle brought Miss Hunter down from London
来假扮她的女儿
in order to impersonate his daughter
这样来摆脱那个年轻人
and get rid of the young man.
是这样的 先生
Well, that was it, sir.
但是富勒先生是一位坚持不懈的人
But Mr. Fowler being a - a persevering gentleman,
就好像一名好水兵一样 封锁了房子
as a good sailor should be, blockaded the house.
后来遇见了你以后 通过各种手段
And having met you succeeded by certain arguments,
金钱还有其他方法
metallic and otherwise,
说服了你 使你相信你和他的利益是一致的
in convincing you that your interests were the same as his?
富勒先生是一位和蔼
Mr. Fowler was a very kind-spoken,
出手阔绰的先生
free-handed, gentleman.
通过这种手段 他设法让你
And in this way he managed that your husband
他设法让你的丈夫不缺酒喝 没锁好门
should not want for drink, the gates unlocked,
确保猛犬被栓好
thus insuring that the mastiff should remain chained,
把一把扶梯准备好
and that a ladder should be ready to assist him
帮助他把爱丽丝小姐救出去
in the rescue of Miss Alice?
如你所说 就是这么一回事
You have it, sir, just as it happened.
于是铜山毛榉那所邪恶房子的
And thus was solved the mystery of the sinister house
谜团解开了
called The Copper Beeches.
鲁卡斯尔先生幸免于死 但已经精神颓废
Mr. Rucastle survived, but was always a broken man,
全凭他忠心耿耿的妻子护理才苟延残喘
kept solely alive through the care of his devoted wife.
还和他们的老佣人住在一起
They still live with their servants,
大概他们知道鲁卡斯尔家过去的事太多
who probably know so much of Rucastle's past
鲁卡斯尔先生很难辞退他们
that he finds it difficult to part from them.
富勒先生和鲁卡斯尔小姐申请特许证书结了婚
Mr. Fowler and Miss Rucastle were married by special license
他现在任职于
and he now holds a government position
毛里求斯岛的政府中
on the island of Mauritius.
亨特女士现在担任
Miss Hunter is now head of
沃尔索尔地区一家私立学校的校长
a private school in Walsall,
我相信她在教育工作上颇有成绩
where I gather she has met with considerable success.
那么 福尔摩斯 你的意见呢?
There, Holmes, your verdict?
非常美好 华生
An admirable account, Watson.
你不认为我加入了太多色彩和活力吗?
Oh,you don't think I've put too much color and life into it?
我亲爱的朋友
Oh, my dear friend
我卑谦的顺从
I humbly defer such considerations
你漂亮的叙述
to your excellent literature.
太好了
Good.